essential.com 2019-05-29

# Privacy Policy

~~Last Updated: May 15, 2018~~

This Privacy Policy explains how Essential Products, Inc. and our subsidiaries (“EP,” “we,” or “us”) collect, use, process, and disclose information about you when you access or use our products and services (such as our devices, websites, mobile applications, and online services), or when you interact with us.

We may change this Privacy Policy from time to time. If we make changes, we will notify you by revising the date at the top of the policy, and in some cases, we may provide you with additional notice (such as adding a statement to our website’s homepage or sending you an email notification). We encourage you to review the Privacy Policy frequently to stay informed about our information practices and the choices available to you.

### **Collection of Information**

**Information You Provide to Us** We collect information you provide directly to us. For example, we collect information when you sign up to receive information about our products or services, create an account or profile, use interactive features of our products or services, make a purchase, participate in our contests, promotions, and surveys, communicate with us via third-party social media sites, apply for a job, request customer support, or otherwise communicate with us. The types of information we may collect directly from you include your name, username, email address, phone number, billing and shipping address, demographic information, and any other information you choose to provide. Additionally, if you use our products or services in connection with products or services offered by a third-party partner, you may provide us with information about your account with the third party in order to enable this functionality, such as the email address and password associated with your account.

In some cases, we may also collect information you provide about others, such as if you decide to purchase and ship products to friends or family. We use this information solely to fulfill your requests, and will not send marketing communications to these individuals, unless they separately opt in to receive communications from us.

When you make a purchase from us, we will collect and store limited payment information from you, such as payment card type, payment card expiration date, and a limited subset of your payment card number in order to process your payment. We do not collect or store full payment card numbers and all transactions are processed by a third-party payment processor.

**Information We Collect Automatically** When you access or use our services or products, we automatically collect information about you, and we may associate it with information that you provide directly to us. For example, we may collect:

  * **Log Information:** We log information about your use of our website, such as your IP address, web browser type and language, access times, referring and exit websites, and clickstream data.

  * **Mobile Device Information:** We collect information about your mobile device when you access or use our mobile applications, such as the hardware model, operating system version, unique device identifiers, Bluetooth signals, mobile network information, and performance and diagnostic data regarding your use of our applications. With your consent, we may also collect precise location information or access information stored in other applications on your device, such as contacts from your address book or photos from your photo gallery.

  * **EP Device Information:** We may collect information about your access to and use of our devices. For example, we may collect information about the following:

    * Device information, such as IP address, device settings and preferences, hardware model, operating system version, network carrier and network technology information, device serial number, Wi-Fi network password, account tokens, user ID, installed applications, device location, and third-party products and services you connect to the device;
    * Performance and log information, such as error logs, power status, app battery usage, system diagnostic logs, and reasons for reboots and network errors (for information about how to control the collection of this information, see “Essential Usage and Diagnostics” below); and
    * Audio and video information for devices that are equipped with a microphone or camera, if you enable or use specific features of our devices.

Note that we collect information from an EP device only when it is connected to the Internet. Additionally, we may associate the information we collect from a device with your account.

  * **Information Collected by Cookies and Other Tracking Technologies:** We use cookies and other similar technologies (e.g., web beacons, pixels, mobile identifiers) on our websites, mobile applications, email messages, and advertisements, to help us understand user behavior, improve our offerings, customize your experience, see which areas and features of our websites and applications are popular, and understand usage and campaign effectiveness. Please refer to our Cookie Policy for more information. 

**Information We Collect From Other Sources** We may also obtain information from other sources and combine that with information we collect through our products or services. For example, we may collect information about you when you post content to our pages or feeds on third-party social media sites.

### **Use of Information**

We may use information about you for various purposes, including to:

  * Develop, operate, and improve our products and services;
  * Provide and deliver the products and services you request, process transactions, and send you related information, such as confirmations, invoices, technical notices, updates, security alerts, and support and administrative messages;
  * Respond to your comments, questions, and requests and provide customer service and technical support;
  * Communicate with you about products, services, offers, promotions, rewards, and events offered by EP and others and provide news and information we think will be of interest to you;
  * Monitor and analyze trends, usage, and activities in connection with our products and services;
  * Detect, investigate, and prevent fraudulent transactions and other illegal activities and protect the rights and property of EP and others;
  * Personalize and improve the products and services and provide advertisements, content, and features that match user profiles or interests;
  * Facilitate contests, sweepstakes, and promotions and process and deliver entries and rewards;
  * Link or combine with information we get from others to help understand your needs and provide you with better service; and
  * Carry out any other purpose conveyed to you at the time the information was collected.

EP is based in the United States and the information we collect is governed by U.S. law. By accessing or using our products and services or otherwise providing information to us, you consent to the processing, transfer and storage of information in and to the U.S. and other countries, where you may not have the same rights and protections as you do under local law.

### **Sharing of Information**

We may share your information as follows and as otherwise described in this Privacy Policy:

  * With vendors, consultants, and other service providers who need such information to perform services on our behalf (such as to send emails or process payments for us);
  * With our third-party partners, if you choose to connect your EP device to their products or services (the information we share with these partners will be described in the authorization screen that is displayed prior to enabling the connection, and you have the ability to stop this sharing at any time by changing your device settings or by contacting our third-party partners);
  * In response to a request for information, if we believe disclosure is in accordance with any applicable law, regulation, or legal process, or as otherwise required by any applicable law, rule, or regulation;
  * If we believe your actions are inconsistent with our user agreements or policies or to protect the rights, property, and safety of EP or others;
  * In connection with, or during negotiations of, any merger, sale of company assets, financing, or acquisition of all or a portion of our business by another company;
  * Between and among EP and any current or future parents, subsidiaries, affiliates, and other companies under common control and ownership; and
  * With your consent or at your direction. 

We may also share aggregated or de-identified information with third parties.

### **Third-Party Products and Services**

You have the ability to install or connect third-party products and services (such as mobile applications) on or to our devices, and to purchase third-party products and services through us. When you use third-party products and services, their terms apply to your use of those products or services. This Privacy Policy does not apply to information collected by such third parties, and we encourage you to learn more about their privacy practices before using their products or services.

### **Social Sharing Features**

Our websites and mobile applications may offer social sharing features and other integrated tools (such as the Facebook “Like” button), which let you share actions you take on our services with other media, and vice versa. Your use of such features enables the sharing of information with your friends or the public, depending on the settings you establish with the entity that provides the social sharing feature. For more information about the purpose and scope of data collection and processing in connection with social sharing features, please visit the privacy policies of the entities that provide these features.

### **Advertising and Analytics Services Provided by Others**

We may work with third-party social platforms, such as Facebook, to serve ads to you as part of a customized campaign, unless you notify us that you prefer not to have information about you used in this way by sending an email to advertising-optout@essential.com indicating the email address you wish to have removed from customized ad campaigns.

### **Security**

EP implements security safeguards to protect your information from loss, theft, misuse, unauthorized access, disclosure, alteration, and destruction. 

### **Transfer of Information to the U.S. and Other Countries**

EP is based in the United States and the information we collect may be transferred, processed, and stored in the United States and other countries, where you may not have the same rights and protections as you do under local law. By accessing or using our products or services or otherwise providing information to us, you consent to the processing, transfer, and storage of information in and to the United States and other countries.

### **Privacy Shield**

We comply with the EU-U.S. and Swiss-U.S. Privacy Shield Frameworks (collectively, the “Privacy Shield”) with respect to personal data we collect from the EU and Switzerland and transfer to the U.S. For more information about the Privacy Shield, and to view our certification, please visit the [Privacy Shield website](https://www.privacyshield.gov/welcome). We remain responsible and liable under the Privacy Shield for any personal data that we share with third parties for external processing on our behalf, as described in the “Sharing of Information” section above, unless we prove we are not responsible for the event giving rise to the damage. If you have an inquiry regarding our certification, contact us at privacy@essential.com. Privacy Shield participants are subject to the authority of the U.S. Federal Trade Commission. You may also refer your complaint to [JAMS](https://www.jamsadr.com/eu-us-privacy-shield), EP’s designated Privacy Shield dispute resolution provider. In certain circumstances, the Privacy Shield provides the right to invoke binding arbitration to resolve complaints (see [Annex I to the Privacy Shield Principles](https://www.privacyshield.gov/article?id=ANNEX-I-introduction) for more details).

### **Your Choices**

**Data Retention** Our data retention periods are based on business needs and legal requirements. We store the information we collect about you for as long as is necessary for the purposes for which we originally collected it, or as needed to provide the products or services to you, unless a longer retention period is required or permitted by applicable law.

You may request that we delete your information, but note that we may retain certain information as reasonably needed to comply with law, meet regulatory requirements, or for legitimate purposes. We may also retain cached or archived copies of information about you for a certain period of time.

You may also ask us to provide you access to, or a copy of, your information, or correct the information we have about you.

If you wish to make these requests, please [submit a support request](https://support.essential.com/hc/en-us/articles/115015511988-Submit-a-support-request).

**Essential Usage and Diagnostics** You can turn Essential usage and diagnostic services on or off at any time by navigating to Settings on your product. If you change your settings after we have initiated a data upload, your new settings will go into effect after that process has been completed. Note that even if you turn this feature off, your device will still send certain device information (such as device serial number, network carrier information, country, and operating system version) needed for critical services such as system or security updates. 

**Promotional Communications** You may opt out of receiving promotional communications from EP by following the instructions in those communications. If you opt out of receiving promotional communications, we may still send you non-promotional emails, such as those about your account or our ongoing business relations.

**Mobile Push Notifications/Alerts** With your consent, we may send promotional and non-promotional push notifications or alerts to your mobile device. You can deactivate these messages at any time by changing the notification settings on your mobile device.

### **Residents of the European Economic Area**

We will process your data where we have lawful bases to do so. Lawful bases can include consent (e.g., if you sign up for a promotion), to perform our responsibilities under our contract with you (e.g., to provide products and services to you, process payments), and for our legitimate interests, provided that the processing doesn’t outweigh your rights and freedoms.

We rely on several legitimate interests in processing your data. For example, we process your data to detect and prevent fraud, understand our users and industry trends, develop and improve our products and services, and send you marketing communications.

Where we rely on consent to process your data, you have the right to withdraw your consent at any time. You may also have a right to object to, or request that we restrict, certain processing of your personal data. 

Residents of the European Economic Area may also lodge a complaint with the supervisory authority where they reside.

### **Contact Us**

If you have any questions about this Privacy Policy, please [email us](mailto:privacy@essential.com) or write us at Essential Products, Inc., 380 Portage Ave, Palo Alto, CA 94306, United States.
